[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, people think jhāna is something you can enter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't enter jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna enters you, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: A mode of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the consequence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll get to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why we said there is no I am in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't say I am in jhāna, I'm entering jhāna, I was in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It subsides.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you think jhāna is something you can enter, literally, something waiting for you to enter it, that's not jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is it worth saying that in the... often in the translations of the jhānas, it says that one enters upon and dwells in jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't say that in Pāli.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it says one dwells in jhāna, having acquired it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having upāsāṃpajñā, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever... even entity, if you want to translate it like that, but the point is...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something that's already happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Based on the consequence of jhāna, of your mode of being, now, you know you acquired it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: I acquired it and thus I entered it and then that's how I dwell in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is usually the perception of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Meditation technique, object, having an overwhelming experience, surge of pleasure or whatever, or I enter jhāna, now I am in the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's completely wrong order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when I say jhāna enters you, it's more accurate to regard it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically, as I said, mode of being or even becomes your point of view, your new point of view, point of view that doesn't see I am as first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... it's a point of view that's... that involves a different order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, and that's a... that's a result.
[SPEAKER_01]: of certain contemplations, certain understanding, certain development of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... if you wonder which type of development of the mind, just read literally any jhāna description.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says it clear as a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at the top of my head, quite secluded from... Seclusion from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is absolutely no description of the first jhāna
[SPEAKER_01]: That does not say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that that's just one way you can enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is the result of your seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seclusion is not because of your jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is because seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you have any doubt about that, it's in the within the same description.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pleasure of the first jhāna is not of the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pleasure is of the seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Viveka jhāna, so pīti-sukhaṅga-viveka jhāna, so it's the bliss and joy and happiness born of the seclusion from sense-desire or sensuality and other wholesome states which pertains to any kind of bodily hindrances of any kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the common notion is, I enter jhāna, then I feel pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not pleasure of jhāna, but pleasure of seclusion, which is what jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, at the time, that's what your point of view becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what your being is.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no room for I am experiencing this pleasure, I am entering, I am exiting this jhāna and what not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, very clear, partly, yet the entire contemporary notions are about watching your nostrils, having the ecstatic experience...
[SPEAKER_00]: Stopping thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop your thinking, of course, and then you have this surge of pleasure and there must have been jhāna there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the standard idea of jhāna being absorption, involving not thinking, you know, you can't have the idea of thinking with jhāna, and yet these words vittaka-vicāra appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are the main characteristic of the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you get these strange translations of... it's not really thinking, it's like a sustained thought and applied...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's literally thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vittaka-vicāra always go together as well, and it literally is just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Amplifying the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: With thinking, with pondering, with things going on in his mind, that's the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't say, oh, with thinking, the first factor, with pondering, with the second factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor is it, yeah, applied and sustained thought and in some sort of concocted method that you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's with thinking and with pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just with, with wandering, with roaming about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they're not really different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just slightly two different aspects, I suppose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of your thinking, which are kind of in separate, practically speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Near synonyms to talk about, maybe, different extents.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that, well, that's another extremely gratuitous notion of my thinking will stop in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had this experience where I was not aware of myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, not just thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the senses stopped.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of anything, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, in Mahajanma 111, every single jhāna has this absolute clarity of mindfulness as its basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And brings mindfulness to the fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: This phenomenon, this phenomenon, seeing all of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: See what's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, it's imperturbable mindfulness, not the absence of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how you want to develop first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seclude yourself from centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you seclude yourself from centrality?
[SPEAKER_01]: By understanding the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The extent of your involvement, the extent of your engagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: The basis, the necessary basis for your engagement with centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand that, you surmount it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having surmounted it, you will know that you surmounted it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then that pleasure of relief, which is a pleasure of the first jhāna, it will be felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the first jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The result of that development, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could see how, like, even back in the day, jhāna, as we discussed before, even in in old Vedas and stuff, meant contemplation, investigating even, thinking over, pondering over something, like either virtues of a deity that you want to develop in yourself, or anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point was,
[SPEAKER_01]: You dwell on it, in order to develop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you think about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not like trying to negate the whole idea of thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to surmount your thinking, that's the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't surmount the second... your thinking if you haven't even developed it properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If all you do is go around denying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but jhānas involve a particular theme.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: We think of jhānas as particularly directed mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why in all those other, in some other suttas, it's like, you can develop jhāna on the basis of mindfulness of the corpse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: We develop jhāna on the basis of mindfulness of the charnel ground, or the, I don't know, discussing the senses, or mindfulness of breathing, or body postures.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... it's not an automatic method.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a way of regarding things on the basis of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the basis of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Way of regarding what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Way of regarding sensuality whereby you remind yourself the extent of it that you know you're free from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Dwelling that, that is the bliss of the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, like the... the first jhāna is not developed by magically entering it and then having pleasure from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual technique, the practice of meditation of the first jhāna, is the practice of understanding the central extent, the extent of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your practice of first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's impossible to engage in sensuality on the level... on the basis of first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the one with the right view, on the basis of first jhāna, would be free from sensuality, even when he's not anymore in the first jhāna, because he would have seen this... he would have been seeing clearly its nature of... of actually being repulsive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's just to basically convict the idea that you can not be celibate and not keep the precepts and have... and enter jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: On a necessary basis, for the consequence of jhāna, first jhāna, is quite secluded from sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite removed, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Separated from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite as in very, as in, as in, basically, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quite as in indeed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indeed, he's separate from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's developed that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's, every time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Separate from, from sensual states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Separate from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasure arises as a result of the recognition of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He cultivates that very thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how he abides in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would dwell in the first jhāna, having acquired it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whether he sits, walks, extends his arms, goes to the toilet, whatever he does while he dwells in the first jhāna, it's divine, because his mind is in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what vihārata means, dwelling.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean temporarily overwhelmed by something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means literally you're dwelling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while you're dwelling in this kuti, you eat, you drink, you lay down, you sit.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing these things while you're dwelling in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence the same principle of the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, more specifically,
[SPEAKER_01]: Practicing that... well, practicing the first jhāna, which means practicing with separation from unwholesome states and sensuality, is done not by chasing down the sensual states, but by seeing a common basis to all unwholesome states, to all five entrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the five entrances are the five that are abandoned in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality, ill-will, restlessness, laziness, distraction, doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: What all of those things have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the necessary basis, necessary container?
[SPEAKER_01]: Body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Body being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, even when people were to engage with them,
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, you were overwhelmed by hindrance and you give in to sensuality or expression of will or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not really leaving the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not actually going further into these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just basically increasing their density, so to speak, density of their significance, within the same basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why anger is felt bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality is felt bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doubt is felt bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's so... some people... that's not so obvious, that doubt is... Yeah, but how... like, how do you know that doubt is unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you feel it unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your body is a fake.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't sleep at night.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's more bodily than that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the body is the necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: For... for any... any of the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But does that mean that the hindrances hinder you because of the body?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sensuality cannot be manifested, cannot be even conceived theoretically, without the basis of body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or anywhere else except within the basis of body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is that its... is that its hindering aspect?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it a hindrance, in other words?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a hindrance when... when you... when you don't put the body first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when is it that you don't put the body first, as a necessary basis?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you put yourself first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what does that mean, in regard to between you and the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: What kind of relationship is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, again, it all comes, sort of, being rooted in sense of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, because this body is unknown to me, in any other terms, except as mind, that's why I'm affected by these things that are bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why we compare the five senses, the five bodily senses, the five bodily domains, as five wild animals that have their own respective domains for feeding.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't possibly, sort of, go and deplete
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can stop being appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can stop appropriating, basically, them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You also have no say over their preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no say over their preferences.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: What the I likes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean you're not responsible for giving in to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, it's like my eye likes this, the tongue likes this, but that, on the level of recognition, a fact of preference, does not mean automatic engagement with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, based on that pull, based on this animal wants to go and feed down there, I give in and I let it do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's very responsible for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not for its arising, but it's basically for its perpetuation, for being, for engaging with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you hinder yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, by basically allowing yourself to be dragged along by those senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how you allow yourself to be dragged along?
[SPEAKER_01]: By taking the ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as you said, the ownership means wrong order, as we discussed in previous talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, which is the right order then?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the order of central pull, or expression of ill-will, or doubt?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the order?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that comes first in that experience?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seemingly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But more specifically, it's the particular hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, that is coming first.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, now I have... my mind is affected by doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I go around, and I and I search, and I talk, and I find, because I do all these bodily things to get rid of this core of my experience, which is the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And everything that you're doing is rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, would that doubt be manifested there, felt unpleasantly, if the body is not there on its own beforehand?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you, if basically recognize mindfulness of the body, recognize that could be the container of
[SPEAKER_00]: Body, without which...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, then mindfulness is established whereby it doesn't matter the hindrance, you don't pervert the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you become quite secluded from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have quite removed the necessary basis for sensuality to take over you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Necessary basis which is that perversion of that order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, basically...
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why your actions have to have been purified beforehand as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to say no to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to practice sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: In order, then, to discern the necessary basis for those things, if they were to be done, and then you stop maintaining that basis, which is the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the hindrances are now seen as... As belonging to the body that doesn't belong to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I wanted to say, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means they don't hinder you anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means they're not hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're fully bound up in, contained in, rooted in something which...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're fully bound up and rooted in the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they always were.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why recognition of that, full understanding of that, frees you from them forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just while you're looking at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, yeah, you have to keep looking at it to be free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you fully understood hindrances... That's why arahant is the destroyer of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when there is sleepiness, it's the body that is sleeping.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the doubt can never be the fundamental doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be like, oh, is this... did he say this or did he say that?
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that doubt can become the hindrance how it used to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you... could you use feeling as... as... as a basis to some of the hindrances?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, any... any... any reference for mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any mindfulness... Because they're all contained within feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the body... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, just...
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason we're talking about jhānas, that's why I'm not talking about the feelings now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is a particular type of mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the body witness is the one who has developed the whole jhāna practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same principle, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's mindfulness of the body, particularly directed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you practice jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And particular direction is the direction of... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we established that the necessary basis for any hindrance, to hinder you, any lust, any aversion, is you taking up the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you take up the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the means of taking up the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is taking up of the body perpetuated?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is it manifested?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just the natural state.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the... No, but ignorance needs maintenance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is not a static thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, greed, hatred, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How are those things manifested?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you talk about greed, hatred and delusion without greedy, hateful, deluded acts?
[SPEAKER_01]: By body, by speech or by mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can those things be perpetuated without intention behind it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're basically taking up the body by acting with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Action is with ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorant intentions in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you act with the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you act like this, you act like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, you need to start restraining the body, in terms of obvious unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obvious sensuality, obvious ill-will, obvious distraction, obvious unskillful states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Precepts, sensual strikes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not negotiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the first way of engaging with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bodily acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doing things with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you can have mind raging with your will, or sensuality, but if the body remains there, left alone, you're not giving in to the pressure to act with it, there is no expression of that, which means whatever unwholesome is, it's not in the domain of the body, because you're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it could be in the domain of speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the second bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, it's kind of more obvious for people to see, okay, bodily actions are bodily, and mental actions are mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech is a type of converging point in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you have verbal thoughts, which are not speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they are bodily expressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how is that possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is... How is speech possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: ... possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't speak without thoughts of speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, thoughts of speaking, even verbal, loud thoughts in your mind, are not the speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that were the speech the Guru has said, that's the speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, speech is when you break into speech physically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what constitutes speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, verbal thinking is not the speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, there is no speech without verbal thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the problem there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there a problem there?
[SPEAKER_00]: We hear something about...
[SPEAKER_00]: Generally, one's assumptions about what's... about speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speech is generally assumed to involve, kind of, me breaking out, breaking forth, pouring out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And me always being mental, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have three ways of engaging.
[SPEAKER_01]: By body, by speech, and by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: My body needs to be restrained beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind is too subtle to see directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the middle bit, the converging point, is where the speech is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically where the assumption takes... where the perversion takes place.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I call it a converging point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's... See, the speech in itself is physical.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sounds uttered by your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it is bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's also...
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a hybrid domain, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's the first one to cease, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body doesn't cease up until like 4th jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, that's a digression.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, it's another type of engagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you engage through your physical actions when you assume the ownership of it, when you're projected towards pleasure from the senses, you assume pleasure in these objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I act, I get them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's already a perversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're basically moving out towards the pleasure out there with your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you assume that to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think the pleasure is over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have to engage bodily with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And body engaging with it is you accessing that pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're getting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with the speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just now, it's not so much into the senses, but it's more between the body and the point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Between the mind and the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Between the verbal thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you think, like everybody, when you speak, the whole notion behind, or even before you speak, the notion behind is, I have thoughts, I have sentences, I have words in my mind, I have the whole voice, and then that kind of flows into the speech out there, and it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can a mental thought flow into the material body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Two separate domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two separate domains that are simultaneously present and never occur without each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the root of the confusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing the nature of that particular saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the definition of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why one breaks into speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even when you speak, your thoughts can never become the bodily sounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they're always simultaneous with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are no bodily sounds without thoughts being there present.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, sort of phenomenologically, when you're speaking, that speech sort of takes the place of your thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: That does...
[SPEAKER_01]: I see that's the assumption of Bhutuja.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who hasn't developed jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think that your speech is taking... How can... How can a physical utterance of these sounds, these vibrations, take place of your thought?
[SPEAKER_01]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having fully discerned that, to that extent, you still own and possess, through perversion, the domain of the body, which is the domain of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fully discern the separateness of it, inherently, impossible to join together, you will then experience the relief of the pressure of the senses that were exhibited on the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the speech will cease in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to cultivate that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensory strength needs to be done first, and maintained throughout, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, practice anchoring of your peripheral awareness, as we spoke before, as in recollecting of your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recollecting the fact that you're not speaking while you're thinking verbally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're cultivating, basically,
[SPEAKER_01]: Discernment of the two simultaneous domains, that they're inseparable from each other, but you're not confounding them anymore, because you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech and thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech and the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're like vāci-sankhāra, the determination of your speech, because it's inseparable from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's it's that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's it's not discerning...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, just to Vīṭaka-vichāra, thinking and pondering is the determination for speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking and pondering is anything... You can't have speech without thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're in separate forms.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, see, in that practice of anchoring your mindfulness in the absence of speech, the mouth that's factually
[SPEAKER_01]: quiet, not producing sound.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can then understand the extent of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without confusing it for speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, the the... That's why silence
[SPEAKER_01]: Physical solitude and not careless chit-chat and so on is absolutely necessary and the Buddha could have not been, like, cleared and have a more hard-line stance on it than he did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thinking that the thoughts... that the speech stands for the thoughts is the same thing as basically saying that the thoughts kind of become speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, you aren't seeing the... these two separate domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you can ask, well, why is the speech converging point?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just how things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how the aggregates are ordered.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not up to you to decide.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you're confounding it, means there is ignorance in regard to that entire basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whenever there is ignorance, there is the automatic appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having sort of distanced yourself from
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense, desire, sensuality, unwholesome restraints.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-distraction, no careless projects and little whatever, however meaningful it might present itself, no little activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all that is rooted in distraction or sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you're completely free from those things, in which case, you wouldn't be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, having practiced that, you also need to practice physical solitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean you, you like, you never see people, you never talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you talk only with the purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not pressure or need.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the purpose.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cultivate that, like, as the Buddha said, the monks train themselves in little speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Speaking little.
[SPEAKER_00]: Put limits on their speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's only when necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: All that is to support your mindfulness of the factual recognition
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a form of thought, but it's a factually correct thought, that you are not speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, my mind can be shouting mad, but I can simultaneously, through that, peripherally discern that my mouth is not uttering any sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there is no wrongly assumed connection between my thought...
[SPEAKER_01]: The moment I forget that my mouth is not uttering the sounds, I can very well, basically, immediately jump back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Into the entire... Form a link.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not being aware of it, it's automatic link.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's automatic sort of mess, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clutter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you dwell long enough, that's why you should cultivate jhānas, don't be negligent, make effort, discern and so on, like in so many suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because you will become so familiar with the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess you can call it relationship between the presence of a mouth able to utter sounds
[SPEAKER_01]: In the presence of verbal thinking, the two separate domains, but you will also then fully understand that doesn't matter how careless you are, verbal thoughts can never enter the extent of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's always thinking and pondering, one breaks into speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like literally two simultaneous things, no other form of connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any form of connection means form of misconceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the not speaking can... it's like... can be the... the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is your... the container of your thinking and pondering, the extent of your thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you remain mindful of... again, and the reason why you can remain mindful is because you're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are not, I'm mindful of my mouth, I'm mindful of my mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're simply mindful of the thought that the mouth is not speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a negative form of doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, if somebody listens to this, they might think, like, oh, mindful of the sensations in your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just to know you're not speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be mindful of all the sensations and still cause the confusion between your thoughts and the domain of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not about what you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about the basis of you not making any sounds while there is verbal thinking going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, if... if you've got, like, a clear background, it's this... the fact that I'm not speaking,
[SPEAKER_00]: To whatever it is I'm thinking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that to me...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you lapse within that whatever you're thinking about, you can't lapse for as long as you don't start making sound with your mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If your mindfulness has been properly anchored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with, like, mindfulness of the body posture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how much you forget, when you recollect it, you recollect the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was always, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The posture hasn't changed, the mouth hasn't spoken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mouth starts speaking, stop speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you again, re-establish the anchor.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I was going to say was then, then it's like that background...
[SPEAKER_00]: ...of the fact that I'm not speaking, that provides a background for the domain of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it basically allows for the unification of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a form of unification of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the extent of mind, because it's seen against this background, within the fact that I'm not speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thinking and pondering is basically, literally, the entire extent, from anything, from the subtlest thoughts to the most coarse verbal
[SPEAKER_01]: Having a song repeated in your mind that you can't shut down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all the domain of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you, based on that, are thinking about your mouth... That's anything that appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the extent of the all in that... in that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you fully understand that any dhamma that manifests in the first jhāna is clearly seen
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, all the five aggregates are clearly seen as not mine, not belonging to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why first jhāna is the necessary base for the culmination of wisdom, to be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, clarity of mindfulness, because it's the clarity of imperturbable order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That this is the container of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's inconceivable, doesn't matter how much I forget, how careless I get, it's inconceivable that this can become that, or vice versa.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of bodily remains the container of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just the way it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, you know, you can... if your mindfulness is developed to the extent necessary on account of, you know, mindfulness of breathing or mindfulness of death, doesn't matter, you can then turn that extent of your mindfulness
[SPEAKER_01]: To the mindfulness of the converging point of natural body... natural engagements between you and the body, so to speak, between the mental and the physical.
[SPEAKER_01]: And establish jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then take it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, from the... for the second jhāna, I won't dwell into it too much, because this is more than enough, and people will start thinking about second jhāna without even understanding what the first is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, from the point of view of the second jhāna, the thinking and pondering is the physical.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the container.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within which?
[SPEAKER_01]: Unified mind that doesn't... That's why second jhāna is called noble silence, by the way, not the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: First jhāna, you can't speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the noble silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, noble silence.
[SPEAKER_01]: The silence is when the mind stops speaking as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you want to stop thinking, you've got to stop speaking with your mind, which is the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you won't get there until you get the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you won't get the first one for as long as you think you can get it, as a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can get it by cultivating the basis for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a consequence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a consequence, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, if it were not consequence, it would be something you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then we're going to say, like, oh, you can't say in jhāna, I am entering the first jhāna, I'm practicing the first jhāna, I'm obtaining the first jhāna, I'm leaving the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean you're not aware of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the reason why you can't say.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't say, because it's... you're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's result of things you've done, such as surmounting sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anchoring your peripheral recollectedness in the fact that factually mouth is abstaining, not speaking, not uttering sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's been doing so for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, you know, like, having... having been secluded from sensuality, sensual pleasure, a joy from seclusion arises, one abides in jhāna, having acquired it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean, you know, as I said before, like, maybe took you a whole month to surmount the sensual domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before then, the result of your abiding in that state becomes the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it can take you half a day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes more, sometimes less, depending how careless you were, if you were careless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, once you cultivate it long enough, it's done at will.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, it's not... See, you know, whenever they would say, oh, I don't need all of this, because whoever can obtain jhānas, it will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like when Mahākassapa said that, for example, I don't need all these luxuries.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because as far as we can obtain jhānas at will, he's like the greatest, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's saying that as a matter of fact.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why there is a praise, oh, you can obtain jhānas at will, is because he's done all the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you wouldn't... Well, mind you, even a mind would take praise on account of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But a rational mind, mind that is authentic, will recognize, well, there is a praise of random things that you have nothing to do with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look how tall you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no say in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But look how virtuous you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look how well kind of mannered or well-read or intelligent and reasonable you are, because you made the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is a legitimate praise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you invested... jhānas is the utmost effort you can make, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's the best praise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whoever can attain it with will, means not he was lucky to get them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means he done so... such an extent of this anchoring mindfulness proper work, that literally, at will, everything is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because he just, you know, won the jackpot and it just happens to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he's so lucky.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you praise that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you're lucky and nothing to do with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So anchoring your mindfulness in the recognition of a mouth that is not uttering sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is a converging point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind you, when it comes to speech, writing, typing, all those would be means of physical converging of your expression.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the chief of them is the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, again, sensuality is inherently inseparable from the notion of your mouth as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the first point of engagement with sensuality when you're a toddler, breastfeeding, eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the first point of satisfaction and it always remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as I said, your sensuality can proliferate, your preferences can proliferate, the expression of your real will can proliferate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, it's all still within the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just its density keeps increasing the more you engage with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it cannot become anywhere else, except from the container of the mouth, because that's the first point of engagement with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first point of confusion, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a convergence between mind and body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind is there, body is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, for you, mouth is kind of... pertains to the mental and pertains to the physical.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is that possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not fully clarifying that, that's how you own both.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or that's how you get affected by both.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, that's why the recognition of that... that is actually impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable for... doesn't matter how verbal thinking is, it's inconceivable for it to become the sounds from your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: The way it happens is just on this level, on these two simultaneous levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you fully understand that it doesn't matter what kind of thoughts you had, how threatening, fearful, you will not be afraid, nor threatened, because you realize, oh, that's where this is manifested, and it's actually inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so now, that's going back to, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with your will, by the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not to... we were talking... you talked about bodily restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Erm...
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, having thoughts of ill will, say, but just making sure that you don't do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you're sort of describing the... how to restrain yourself on the verbal level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which then restrains your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason your mind was not restrained is because it was under the assumption that it can pertain to that which concerns me, which is the external world of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you realize the mind can never step into it, nor can it become the mind either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just physical, mental, bodily, and on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure, fundamentally, it's all mental, in terms of it's all dhamma manifesting itself, but that's a different approach.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the approach of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is about understanding this converging point between...
[SPEAKER_01]: Points of engagement with the body, which is a necessary basis for any sensuality to affect you, to pressure you, to pertain to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that order becomes uncorruptible, by your ignoring, by your carelessness, you're abiding in that which you've acquired, which is the right order, which is where jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're always wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have unwholesome jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because unwholesomeness is defined, as we said before in other talks, by the perversion of the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a definite... That's why unwholesome things are unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they contain a contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Repulsive as attractive.
[SPEAKER_01]: In jhāna, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's impossible for them to be unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, again, in first jhāna...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we said at the beginning that
[SPEAKER_00]: Overcoming sensuality involves putting the body first, recognizing, not putting it first, but seeing it, seeing that it is first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing that it is first, discerning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a necessary... and not like first initially and then change it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It remains first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter the extent of sensual pressure, engagement, it remains first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, you discern even a more specific manifestation of that order of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is again, body first, which is the...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still that... Because that's exactly what sanctuary is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the container.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body and the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to everything that the body can go for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rather than the usual kind of, I use my body or I...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way that that mindfulness of presently enduring
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-speaking mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way that can become intelligible is on the basis of thorough sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Celibacy, withdrawal from sensuality, ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get to understand all the other hindrances as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, that doesn't matter how much
[SPEAKER_01]: Sleepiness, restlessness might be like... how heavy it might be, you won't be bearing that weight for as long as you don't pervert the aura of what comes first, which is the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So this is... whether you want it or not, it cannot be anywhere else except on the body, the domain.